thank you all for coming I know it's a
long way to come here uh we tried to
choose a place in the middle of the
world so it means everybody has to
travel a little bit
okay thank you for coming and I know
it's a long way and I know it's a lot of
money and I Know It Tak some
fun and uh I'm happy to come happy to
finish this book with you uh this is
called L
RM and it's the steps to the path to
Enlightenment and I always tell the
story I was sitting with my wife and her
mother uh many years ago and her mother
enjoyed reading
books and she asked me m she call me
m the funniest thing she used to say
when I'm
driving mom will sit in the back and
uh I just say m I said what
you could drive a little
faster she's 90 something too I think
she accused me of driving to scho but uh
she asked me what's your favorite book
in your life and this is my favorite
book in my life and I love books you
guys know and you know we have saved 12
million pages of
book but this is my favorite book and my
teacher taught me this book three times
uh it took 30
years I'm actually pretty
fast uh only 303
years we can finish pretty soon this uh
as you probably
know uh was a teaching given by my
teacher teacher
teacher named Pabon and his student
was was a young
llama in in in Tibet llama means
incarnated llama uh it doesn't mean
llama in in the monastery llama means
you are the Incarnation of another
person and usually the llamas are little
bit irritating young guys and uh many of
them hit me with their bicycles and
things like that and uh but he was very
unusual and I guess I don't know how old
he was maybe maybe 20 or 25 but he he
sat in the teaching for 24 days I think
1921 or something like that and he
listened to the teaching by his teacher
and then he made
notes and uh he worked on those notes I
think for 15 or 20 years and uh he made
this book called uh some people call
Liberation in the palm of your hands the
the real title is a gift of
Liberation uh put into the palm of your
hand uh so I like to call it a gift of a
gift in the hands or something like that
and it means you don't have to try too
hard to get enlightened you just come
try not to fall asleep even if you fall
asleep there's a
blessing and they put the enlightenment
in your hand and you don't have to do so
you don't have to work so hard it's kind
of like a gift free gift you know and uh
it's that's the name of the book
and it was the greatest book I think
ever written in tibetan language so this
is sort of a
monument to the Tibetan language the
Tibetan language
died about uh 50 years ago 45 years ago
it was
killed and uh it's gone uh the as a as a
language uh it's been destroyed uh so
this is the greatest
book uh in the Tibetan language I think
and it's a poetry it's pure poetry and
so I I like
to when I teach
lumm I like to uh read the the Tibetan
I'd like to read it to you and uh I know
maybe you're not interested in tibetan
but many people said that before and I
hooked them so uh I think it's a
blessing to hear uh this language
linguistically Tibetan
uh is is not related to any language in
the world it's a very strange language
uh if there's a tradition that says it
dropped out of the sky and I almost
believe it like uh all of the languages
in the we say from Iceland to
Iran uh they all come from Sanskrit
Greek Latin German English but uh this
this language is from somewhere else
from some other realm and it's a
beautiful language so I I hope you will
get some seeds to learn it and but don't
feel pressure just enjoy relax this is
the class where uh I also get to relax I
wear my usual clothes I don't have to
wear Sage
suit and uh I kind of enjoy myself and I
hope you enjoy yourself also so just
relax and
enjoy and uh I you know I sat through 30
years of these classes and and it feels
like we're not trying to finish a book
it feels like your whole life for the
rest of your life uh I hope we can have
long room so I I don't have
any idea to finish anytime soon okay I'm
not thinking uh we should finish and
move on to the next thing it's kind of
for me uh I spent 25 years with my
teacher in the same house and he taught
this book uh every week or
something and uh it was wonderful and
it's sort of uh Comfort to have someone
to teach you the
L every every week or every month for
your whole life uh I I think it's like
going to the gas station in your car and
you run around for a week and you you go
crazy in your job and and then you come
back to the gas station called L room
and you fill up uh your spiritual side
and then you run around again for a week
and then you you go back to the L room
so for me it doesn't have to start it
doesn't have to finish you know it's
it's just kind of a comfort for your
whole life and I hope we can continue as
long as possible uh we will Tim
mentioned
um we've we started in 2010 we've been
on it for 13 years and uh I did some we
are 92% done with the
text and uh my plan uh when I started
this book 13 years
ago uh at the the end of the book they
teach you uh meditation shamanta and
vasana uh they teach you how to meditate
and they teach you about emptiness at
the end of the
book uh because it's the final two of
the bodh saas
Perfections and uh I
thought because there's a tradition to
meditate on LM every time you learn a
few
pages of LM it's tradition to to
meditate on it and try to incorporate it
in your life and then move on to the
next step so I
thought uh we should go to the end of
the book and learn how to
meditate and then uh we go back to the
beginning of the book because we're
supposed to meditate on each of the
steps and so I when I started 13 years
ago I I went to the end of the book and
I taught the last two Perfections
meditation and wisdom they are
unusually short in this book this book
is a thousand
Pages uh but and by the way which is
8,000 pages in
English uh and uh but I went to the end
it's kind of
short the the section on meditation and
on emptiness at the end it's kind of
short
because he had SAS
room and that was written
about 500 years before this one and that
one's a similar Pages it's about a
thousand Tibetan Pages which is about
8,000 English pages and uh in that
one uh the presentation of meditation
and emptiness is extremely detailed and
it's one of the greatest uh explanations
of emptiness and meditation in history
so uh I thought when we reach that part
when we come back to the last two
Perfections I will teach you from that
book from Tas great
L and then that's going to increase the
years okay uh because that's about half
of his L room that's about 4,000 pages
in English Okay so and it's awesome and
so that's
dessert okay so we'll finish fin this
book uh and we won't do the meditation
and the wisdom because I finished it
already and then we'll go to the L Chim
and that that will take I don't know
that will take five or 10 years I guess
okay and it's amazing it's really
fantastic okay so we're about 92% done
we've been talking about
uh we've been talking about lojo
okay uh which is how to develop Boda how
to develop a love for all people where
you want to make them Buddhist you want
to make all people Buddhist so we're in
that section where they're talking about
different ways to develop bodh the wish
for enlightenment that's where you want
to become a Buddha so you can help
everybody okay and he's been using um
a book from the kadamba so kadamba
there's a modern uh Buddhist group
called kadamba they took the name from
some Buddhist a thousand years ago uh
these were the early Buddhist in Tibet
first Buddhist in Tibet Tibet was a non
Buddhist country it was Bumbo which is
uh some kind of Shaman Shamanism very
similar to the Siberian
some of the Siberian tribes tangut and
tangeri they call tangeri in Siberia and
these are uh
special Shaman teachings and that was
popular in Tibet then the Buddhists
started to come over the
Himalayas uh from India and at the same
time India was attacked uh by people
from the Middle East and turkey and uh
Buddhism was wiped out in
India completely there's no Buddhist
left in India it was the world's it was
the motherland of Buddhism it's where
Buddhism started but around starting
around 1,00 years ago it was wiped out
completely and uh so it's like a guy
jumping off a ship you know Buddhism
jumped off the ship called India and
jumped into Tibet and then it was
destroyed in India so uh and the
Tibetans didn't even have writing at
that time they just have Yaks and they
are just you know taking care of yaks
and
they they invented an alphabet and they
invented writing for their country and
they started to write down
Buddhism and they went crazy the whole
country went crazy and they become the
greatest Buddhist in history I think and
they you know we're cataloging uh 400
500,000 books they wrote 400 500,000
books on Buddhism and they are high
quality every book is amazing every book
is like
Shakespeare it's unbelievable 500,000
half a million books about Buddhism each
one is different and each one is amazing
and very very accurate highly accurate
So today we're going to study a teaching
that was popular uh 1,000 years ago in
Tibet and it was brought to Tibet by
Lord
arsha uh who was born I think 982 so
1000 and U we're working on a book
SII you want to raise your hand
s uh he's one of our
translators and he's the vice president
of DCI and he works very hard because of
his hard work I get
salary and God bless you and please live
a long life and uh and so I don't have
to worry about money you know I have
this good salary and because of his work
uh and he asked can I be a
translator can I learn how to translate
this was seven or eight years ago and uh
we
started and he finished uh a very great
book of poetry uh that was written 1,00
years ago and right now we are uh
cleaning up the book and uh it's
extraordinary book and it's by someone
named dharmar
rakita and his student was Atia and
Atia was a great Indian Master uh who
came to Tibet he agreed to come for six
months or something and then there was a
war and he stayed for 12 years and he
helped to start Buddism in to bad so uh
this we're going to read some
poetry which is from his times and this
is called uh Lo
dunda it's a
seven topics about how to be become a
Buddha okay and it's very very sweet
if you took the ACI courses I think it's
in course number
14 when I first taught ACI courses in
1990s in New
York uh course number 13 is Buddhist
logic I think Rob was there I don't know
and I I I lost half of my students half
of my students quit really and I was a
little bit worried about it you know uh
so after I finished the logic course I
decid to do loong because it's so
friendly loong is so friendly accessible
powerful sweet you know so I started
lojo and I taught this
lojo uh in that course but he goes a
deeper he goes much deeper so we're
about halfway through uh a book called
The seveno Modo it's not really seven
points it's seven
sections and each section has maybe 20
ideas in it and we're going to we're
going to continue through that okay
that's where we
are and I'll show the Tibetan on the
screen uh where is the screen yeah and
don't get nervous okay you don't have to
learn to
Bon uh you know many people said I'm not
going to learn tobet word Smith said I'm
not going to learn tobet now he's the
best teacher of Tibetan
so just relax learn a few words it's
okay it's like my Japanese or like my
Chinese like
niow
Rim you know and you can learn a few
words it's good luck for your next life
okay so just relax you don't have to
memorize anything this is a comfortable
class I am talking to your
subconscious okay and it will change
your heart uh even you don't want to uh
this teaching will change your heart
okay I'm also going to show pictures
which I call adom adom means Ideal Image
and um I'll show you a picture to help
you remember the main ideas okay you
don't even have to remember the Tibetan
word just remember the picture okay and
each picture will have a meaning okay
and gala's habit is to hand out $100
Bill
uh to people who can tell me what's the
picture okay so just relax and you know
try to remember what the picture means
and this is how I used to memorize the
books like that and I will connect to
people picture to each
idea and then I could memorize a whole
book you know so pictures are very
powerful I think that's why Chinese
language is so powerful so efficient
because it's based on pictures so uh
learn the pictures look at the pictures
try to remember what the picture means
maybe you can win
$100 and actually $100 is usually 100
lifetimes of
Happiness uh if you can answer the
question okay so try to learn the
pictures and I will test you tomorrow
I'll show you the picture and I'll say
who can tell me what's this picture and
then don't be all nervous and don't just
relax and have fun okay l r is fun it's
not like those other courses okay all
right not
like difficult things DCI okay
uh so here's the first picture okay and
I have fun I have fun she in the
pictures and yeah it's a lady saying
goodbye okay and the subject that we're
on is po okay POA means how to die well
okay dying well and I'm not allowed to
teach this stuff in DCI I'm not allowed
to teach this stuff in I'm not allowed
to teach this stuff much in more SI I'm
allowed to teaching and Lear room okay
and this is the important stuff okay so
uh how to die
and how to move on you know
and even if you're not planning on dying
trust me everyone else didn't plan on
dying either but they die people die we
will die so you have to get ready and
you have to know how to die and you know
I went to Princeton University second
year now it's number one in the world uh
the university but they don't teach how
to die there's no course how to die and
uh we are lucky to have L room we are
lucky to have some instructions how to
die well okay and you
know you can learn how to be a doctor
and you can learn how to be an engineer
but you're not sure you're going to be a
doctor and you're not sure you're going
to be an engineer but when you learn how
to
die you're going to use that
degree definitely okay so and learn it
while you're young and then you don't
have to worry later okay okay learn it
now and if you don't die for 20 years
that's nice uh but you might die
tomorrow so it's helpful it's really
helpful and I taught many students who
died okay you are younger you they were
younger than you okay
so all right here we go um she's saying
goodbye let's go back to the Tibetan you
[Applause]
guys
go down you
guys go down down down down go past the
Bold more more more more more these are
just my notes there we go okay
UHA so they're talking about POA POA
means how to die how to die well and how
to go to the next place well po needs to
travel to the next World okay and here
he
says minimum when you die try to
remember the three jewels okay minimum
while you die try to remember the three
jewels Buddha Dharma okay Buddha
Dharma the jewel Buddha Jewel Dharma
Jewel sa is different
from Buddha Dharma not the same thing
Buddha is a person Dharma is the books s
is the mon and nons but the jewel the
sambal sambal three jewels that's a
completely different thing okay and each
one means emptiness each one refers to
emptiness okay Buddha
means uh the real
protector in in Buddhism is the
emptiness of the Buddha okay not not
even the physical body but the emptiness
of the Buddha we don't go to a Buddhist
temple and worship
statues that's not Buddhism okay go to a
Buddhist temple light
incense give it to the Buddha it's not
Buddhism okay Buddhism is to understand
what is a Buddha and the Buddha is
emptiness okay Buddha's emptiness of
Buddha when you take refuge
you take refuge in the the Buddhist
emptiness okay that's that's what can
protect you not Buddha okay uh Dharma
means uh the perception of emptiness
okay B bonaria who sees emptiness
directly that that seeing is Dharma it's
not the books it's not the holy books
it's not the translations it's the
emptiness it's to see emptiness that's
DH that's dharm joke
sa anyone who saw emptiness directly
okay that's real sa so it doesn't we
don't believe in Buddhism that you
worship
Buddha or even the books are Buddhism we
don't believe that it's the emptiness
that the Buddha has it's
the understanding emptiness which is in
the books and it's the people who saw
emptiness directly touched the diamond
world they are real protection those
three things are protection there's a
very famous uh sad
joke that when Buddha was alive uh his
town was attacked and many people said
oh we have Buddha in our town and they
ran to the Buddha's house and they grabb
onto the Buddha's clothes and they they
hold on and then the soldiers came in
and killed them holding the buha holding
the Buddha's room you know and just kill
them they try to take
refuge they go for protection to the
physical Buddha cannot help you can they
all died all those people died okay they
what protects you is the emptiness of
the Buddha The
Emptiness how to say it
positively all things come
from seeds all kind things come from
seeds that's protection
that that can help you that's sow that's
the three jewels okay if you understand
that you you're a Buddhist if you don't
understand that don't think you are a
Buddhist okay once you understand about
the pen you're a
Buddhist
okay I'm not allowed to teach Buddhism
in many
places but I teach the
pen okay okay understand and yeah yeah
yeah
uh and if you don't understand the pen
then you're you're not a Buddhist okay
and it and then can't help you it's not
going to help you okay so here he says
minimum poor minimum poor K Chung means
Min minimum please remember the three
jewels as you die as you die think about
the pen think about emptiness think
about seeds as you die minimum okay
minimum means that will protect you
personally it will not help other people
much okay if you can die as you die
remember seeds where things come
from uh it will help you to die you will
die better you will go to a better place
okay everybody wants to go to heaven
after they die someone asked me a
Chinese person asked me this week
uh now I lay me down to
sleep ask the Lord my soul to keep if I
die before I wake ask the Lord my soul
to take we learn this prayer when we are
six years old five years old it means
it's a Christian prayer and we our
parents teach us uh before we sleep and
we have to recite it to our parents
before we sleep and it means if I die
tonight uh please Jesus Take me or God
please take me
uh it's like that it's a it's a
motivation for when you die okay and in
Buddhism uh if you can die and remember
the seeds you you will have a good po if
you will have a good Reaper okay
everybody's like I don't know hold
this I don't know hold
this rock from holy place where Buddha
was walking or something like that and
when you die try to hold this rock or
something and that's not protection okay
that won't help you much
remember seats remember about seats
while you die and you will go to a good
place everybody you know they do
mantras why are you doing mantras when I
die I want to go to amabas heaven forget
it just remember the pen okay you know
all money pay never sent you to heaven
okay remember the pen and then die then
you you will go to heaven if there's a
joke here later okay about it by the way
this book is when in the beginning of
the book The the writer said we went to
the
talk by my teacher he taught for 24 days
all
day I think no pee PE breaks I don't
know how you he taught for 24 days and
and we went sometimes we cry sometimes
we laugh sometimes we fall
asleep but he's uh you know this one is
kind of funny he says uh just try to
remember about the pen or remember about
seeds and then if you die you're safe
you will go to a good place
yourself if you
have
higher goal if you want to help more
people
then he
says as you die try to remember bod as
you die try to try to think I would like
to help all people in the world okay I'm
dying now and I I wish soon I can become
Buddha to to help everybody I wish that
and then die like that then that's a
perfect po okay that's a good PA you
don't need a vajana tantra secret
way this is B okay I I want to help
everybody die this way and that's a good
death and you will go to a good place
okay that's protecting
yourself okay uh okay by the way you
won't remember all this until you get
really
sick and then you will remember all this
I'm putting information in your mind for
that day you're going to forget it until
then when they put you in the hospital
and the doctor
like or you're gonna your family's like
you're going to be fine you know and the
doctor's
like then you're gonna say gu what I
said
something in Kyoto I
[Music]
remember you know so it's good to have
the
information in your mind and when you
need it you can use it okay hopefully
you don't get hit by a car quickly you
have some good cancer slow cancer and
you have time to remember everything
okay it's better it's really better okay
all right uh next
picture this a nice picture of my wife I
I she's
wonderful she's saved my
life and
uh we like to go riding on the beach and
we have special bicycle to go on the
beach and
um this one's called uh well I'll teach
it to you
first so how do I get to a Buddha
Paradise after I die you know what
should I do as I die okay
uh there is a way you can send yourself
to a Buddha Paradise as you die you can
do it you just have to know how
okaya so chawa is the author of the
seveno loo okay one of the
kadas uh he didn't write it he wrote it
down uh for the public before that it
was kind of secret and aesa learned it
in indones IIA so there are some cool
people from
Indonesia
okay suraya suraya
mostly okay uh so
chawa uh he he was the first person to
publicize it but AA learned it in
Indonesia from suana Guru uh whose name
was also DTI but that's a different DTI
okay uh so anyway anyway chawa da da da
means he was ready to die he was
dying and N chipa he wanted to go to the
hell Realms it's it's a very funny story
so the person who wrote the book that
we're studying this
week who who wrote that he said when I
die my goal is to is to go to the hell
RS okay and I'm going to help people
there he made a plan like that D when he
was getting ready to die he made some
final offerings
CH he got he tried very hard to make
offerings he pray I want to go to n i I
don't not just I want to go to hell to
help the people there when I die I want
to go to the lowest hell okay okay this
hell is
unbelievable Nar means
uh I don't know it's like someone
stabbing you with a knife all the time
no break Nar means no not even two
minutes break it's like stabbing you
with a knife or burning you and he prays
to go there he's praying to go there
because he will help the other
people they say Lord Buddha got bodh in
the hell Realms they say Lord Buddha got
his bodh in the hell rooms okay so he's
cha was like I hope I can go to hell I
hope I can go to hell the worst hell
M then when he was dying he's
like you know and the students like you
okay oh you okay no no I'm not okay and
they're like is it a lot of pain are you
in a lot of pain no no I'm not in pain
what's going on I want to go to hell
what's going on I keep going to I'm
Heaven I don't want to go there and he
got very angry he's very upset he's I
don't know every time I want to help the
help people then the karma is I start to
go up to
the and he's angry he's very upset okay
so don't try try not to have too much
love when you die okay try to be angry
or
jealous and then you can go to help
people
okay and he went to the heaven he went
to amabat heaven he was very upset
like okay because he wants to help the
people in Hell okay so that motivation
po that's real
po means he wasn't able to go to the
hill instead he just could see that he's
going to go to the heavens you know he's
going to go to the Buddha Paradise okay
there was
another started about a thousand years
ago and there was one named
POA and he also did the same okay
uh say there was a case where there was
a mother and a daughter who
were dragged Away by in the river they
fell in the river and the river was they
were drowning in the
river p
s and they each tried to help the other
to survive each one tried to save the
other one okay so each one's trying to
hold up the other one okay uh some Kini
then because their Last Hope was to help
their family person in person they both
went to the Buddha Paradise okay and
it's a very sweet story mom's trying to
save the daughter push her towards the
land daughter's trying to save the mom
and push her towards the land and
because each one is trying to save
another person they both go have to go
to the heaven together okay so that's
that's dying with a higher motivation
okay to die with a higher
motivation okay next picture you
guys yeah by the way if you so when you
see that picture of my wife can you go
back
uh it means
uh it means sometimes you want
to help people if you want to help
people in
suffering uh that Karma will push you to
really beautiful places really really
beautiful place okay even you don't want
to go it will push you so when you see
this picture I want you to say oh Gesa
was trying to
go exhaust himself at some program and
instead he had he was forced to go to
the beach and ride on the bicycle with
vaji yini okay all right okay so uh when
you see this picture you're going to say
oh those people who you try to help
other
people accidentally they go to heaven
they don't want to go okay uh the
picture before
that was you know when you say
goodbye at least try to remember the
three
and if you can remember trying to help
all people then that's a good way to say
goodbye that this is so tomorrow you can
make $100 if you remember you Grandpa's
very easy I mean I give a $100 if you're
even close to the right answer
right okay so just remember a little bit
okay you can get rich this way ask word
Smith
how do you think he support all these
girls you know four
girls right L as a
girl okay yeah all
right
POA let's go to
the let's go to the oh I'm
sorry oh yeah
okay
Kaa means
uh uh inet there's many many rivers
everywhere because that's where the
Himalayan mountains are so the snow
melts a lot and you can walk half a mile
you will hit a river all the four Great
Rivers of this world come from the
Tibetan mountains meong uh the Yellow
River the ganis river these Rivers all
come from the same place so you you
can't you go a little place in tobet you
hit a river and they did not have
Bridges so they had Kaa Kaa means uh you
take tree branches and you make a a
frame and then you take a yak skin and
you make a little boat and they're very
powerful they're very strong you can put
a horse or a couple horses on one and
get them across a that's called
Ka how did I learn that word I learned
all my Tibetan from my teacher my dear
teacher
K and
uh one day the toilet
overflow and all the pooo came out like
on the river and he said oh looks like
Kaa I said what's Kaa he said it's the
leather board in Tibet in looks exactly
like that and they said clean it
up so I always remember okay Ka he says
uh there was a Kaa that was going to
sink p p Chen is the ancient word for an
important me messenger okay what's the
other common word for
Messenger Pon yeah Pon which means uh
your tantric partner okay messenger pan
is another word for the same thing pan
okay p and he sacrificed himself he he
decided he will jump into the river and
he will die so the cor will get lighter
and the other passengers Will Survive so
he volunteered he didn't tell anybody he
just jumped off immediately he jumped
off the core and he died
okay
Mash but he didn't die he wanted to
die so that the other people will
survive
J and then a rainbow came and struck
him and then he was taken off to a
Buddha Paradise okay he jumped in the
river to save the other passengers and
then this rainbow hit him and he
he disappeared on the rainbow this is a
rainbow at Diamond Mountain I just
thought it was a nice rainbow we have
nice rainbows there you should
come if you don't learn to do some deep
retreat in your life you you wasted your
life okay you you can miss a few months
of work you won't remember after six
years or five years okay but uh you got
to do some Retreat okay you got to do
some Retreat do some Retreat okay very
very important okay you you miss a year
of work or something or they don't
choose you vice president of the year or
something that's okay that's not going
to help you when you die but the retreat
will help you I gave up many positions
to do my Retreats and then they came
anyway right it's like jumping in the
water okay so okay
uh then there's a okay let's go to the
next picture or let's go to the text you
ready let's go to the
text
say
fed uh fed is
a very strange word in Tibet there's no
F in tibetan they don't have
F but they have one it's called fat and
uh it means
like it's like another f word you
understand
very strong
word you know like you go this mudra F
you
know and then fat means boom you know
and there's a tradition in
some Tibetan
Traditions when you die if you go fat
fat fat fat you will go to a good place
or
it's called it's called
hick then somehow you go to a holy place
do you think it will
work no it's nothing to do with your
motivation right I mean you can kill
somebody and say hit kick fat fet you
know the word not going to take you to
heaven okay uh but there's some
traditions into that uh mistake it's
mistaken and they say oh just say f f
and if it's
possible to go to a Buddha parano
because you said fat
fat then Buddha won't teach so many
sutras we just have one Sutra called the
fat
Sutra fat
fact you know it's it's funny you know
and they say oh it's secret you know
just say fed you will be born in a
amabas paradise you know so if that's
true why didn't Buddha teach everything
body you know it doesn't make sense you
know Buddha wants everyone to go to
paradise if if you can just say fat fat
and it takes you to the paradise then
why why come to Lam why there's 300,000
scriptures you know if just everybody
can learn hick and fet and it doesn't
make sense and it it doesn't it doesn't
make sense it's not true okay they're
cheating people it's it's like terrible
terrible I call it selling uh fire
extinguishers that don't work it's like
if you're a very bad person and you you
have a fire extinguisher company and you
know they don't work but you sell them
to everybody and then when there's a
fire they
like you know and then they die or it
hurts them you see what I mean to teach
people oh just hi hick F fet you know
it's like selling fire extinguisher
doesn't work it's it's mean to to tell
people that it doesn't work okay all
right uh it's a little bit harder than
that
so fat
F I know you guys are interested in the
in the fat
fat and it's true that some people who
did a lot of
picture if you do a lot of yoga and you
move your Prana sometimes you go f or
you know The Prana will move it's like
burping really okay fat
fat and uh he says look some people do
yoga did it happen to you I don't know
when I stretch certain muscles when I do
my yoga and I stretch the back did you
see me Rob in the gym I'm like burping
if I stretch certain muscles the they
open and the and the wind comes and I'm
like my wife doesn't like
it but that's just that's just Chi
that's just L that's just Prana it's not
uh some spiritual thing it's just
physical thing it's like your stomach
when you're hungry it
goes hereat
here it's not going to help you okay
you're stomach's not giving you secret
Mantra he's just hungry okay so uh it's
just a natural sound that comes out of
your body okay and don't think it's
something special and it's not going to
help you you know don't waste your time
when you do yoga you release Prana and
sometimes you will burp or you will fart
and and that's very good for you The
Prana is moving but it's not going to
take you to heaven okay uh all right so
you cannot reach heaven by
farting ask your
wife she'll let you know especially in
the bed at night right okay sometimes it
happens all
right if you're interested in Y Yoga L
is a good ex can you show that to B
again l means
Prana true means uh movement of Prana uh
what do you call it advantageous
movement of Prana it's just like a burp
or a fart or something the The
Prana
jerks and it moves it's called true and
true core is the ancient ancient word
for yoga Asa and it means machine it
means the machine of the body yantra in
Sanskrit yantra not Tantra but yantra
and it means the machine of the body so
TR here means look there's going to be
some spontaneous movement of The Prana
inside of you but that's not an
enlightened thing and you're not going
to heaven or something it's the same as
burping or
farting which is by the way it's a
healthy thing when you're doing yoga
it's moving pris moving so so be you
know if you're in a group of yogis that
you know them and you know each other
it's fine sweating farting uh burping
these are all healthy for your body uh
during AA practice during AA When you
sweat a lot of poison comes out of your
body that's why you sweat so if you
sweat a lot you're
lucky okay it takes sweat was invented
by the body to carry toxins out of the
body so it's a good thing okay L but he
says here truly look it's just a it's
just a Boop of The Prana PR boop boop
then don't he said don't get excited
okay and if you really want to go to
amabas
paradise after you die the main way is
to pray for other people when you die
okay the main way is to pray for other
people when you die okay that's a trick
about dying Tim what time I go
to 515 do I do
Q&A okay uh I'll start a Q&A uh in seven
minutes okay you I always tell people
you have three choices number one if
you're a good person you asked me
something to do with this
class uh
secondly if you're not such a good
person you can ask me any personal
question I don't care okay and I heard
every question in the
universe I didn't hear a new question
for 20 years or something okay uh so any
terrible question about your personal
life we're all friends we all have the
same problem but we don't want to talk
about it and uh you can ask me personal
questions I don't have any problem at
all I'm fine any question is fine if if
something's bothering you or you have a
personal challenge in your life or your
marriage or your family or something I'm
happy to talk about it and we don't talk
about it outside the room am I right we
don't say oh Maria I had this problem
did you
know okay agree we don't talk about
other people's problems so give people
the freedom to ask a personal question
okay and then thirdly if you want a
philosophy question I'm happy to answer
a philosophy question personally I like
all questions so I don't really care so
it's fine to ask me about the class fine
to ask me about your personal life or
it's fine to ask me about you know some
weird emptiness question like Peter Merl
ask so that's why he's a good teacher
okay
uh
okay okay he said don't you know it's
not a big deal if your body makes some
weird noises when you're doing yoga and
that's not connected to dying well
okay
uh
next
picture okay and uh yeah we're going to
talk about closing the door and it's
called and song means animal rebirth
Hungry Ghost rebirth hell rebirth three
lower rebirths okay go go go kick means
to close the door or slam the door so
the picture if I ask you tomorrow for
$100 uh what's this picture you're going
to say close the door to the lower
Realms as you die as you die there's
certain things you can
use there's certain ideas you can think
about when you die and you cannot be
born in the lower Realms the best one is
the pen the best one is the pen okay if
you really understand the
pen and you're doesn't matter you're
Buddhist or not Buddhist it doesn't
matter at all if you really understand
the pen you cannot take a lower birth
it's not possible okay that's a
unbelievable that's why Grandpa teaches
the pen everywhere even you heard it
before cuz I'm trying to close your
door okay and I don't tell the DCI
audiences and you know that but I never
let them get away without the pen okay
because I'm trying to keep them out of
the lower Ms okay if you understand the
pen well you cannot be born as an animal
you cannot go to the house you cannot be
a ghost you will be born at least as a
human okay so it's important the reason
Grandpa repeats it over and over again
it's not because I
forgot some some guy told me in
Singapore I'm sorry he wasn't from
Singapore okay he said Gua can I get my
money back why you forgot you taught the
pen last year I'm like no I didn't
forget I taught the pen last year I'm
trying to do something else for
you okay all right okay and if you
really want to help people
then teach them the pen over and over
again okay just teach the pen over and
over again I teach it all the time like
on an airplane I I teach it to the
person sitting next to me they think I'm
crazy you know they're like I don't want
to know about that I'm like I don't
care all
right no imagine you save someone from
going to hell in in two minutes on the
airplane that's pretty
good
one lady sit down next to me and I'm
like how can I teach her to pin you know
and she has a book and she she's staring
at me and then she she say she show me
it's The Diamond Cutter Business book
and she pointed to my picture she
said and I'm like yeah and she said she
says I was just wondering if I ever can
meet you in my life I said you need to
know about the
pan it was fun it was in England yeah it
was
cool uh
okay closing the door
uh when you do your PO when you die
with when you die with these
instructions about how to be a good
person okay Paul you don't go and you
don't go fat okay uh but Sub sub means
it's much more deep than those weird
tantric things that some people teach
okay like what do you
call Mah what's it
called
mahra or stuff like that weird stuff M
what's the other
thing zen zen all that stuff forget it
just forget it okay uh teach somebody to
love other people that's the best way to
that's the best tantric way to get to a
good rebirth okay care about other
people take care of other people pray
for other people as you die it takes
discipline you have to do it a
lot
K means if you do all those other things
hi Hick Heck or fat fat fat uh it's not
sure whether you are closing the door to
the lower Realms or not it's not it's
not certain that you will succeed with
all those weird things like Z chin and
all these other things they you don't
need them they're not going to help you
they might work and it might not work so
don't use it okay all
right we want to try to die with the
five
powers and the next part of this book is
called the five powers for dying well by
the way dying you all look too
serious okay you're looking very serious
you know oh KLA teaching dying you know
you should be happy you know you should
be like silly you know like Su gang you
should be like he's I'm going to die I'm
going to die so goddamn good you know
this is great this is great stuff you
know I'm so happy he not teaching DCI
you know we're learning how to die
finally somebody teaching me how to die
God bless you know and you should be
happy and relaxed if you know how to die
it's like not a big thing okay and you
can see where you're going you know when
you're going you know where you're going
afterwards and you just relax about it
okay it's like taking a Subway or
something okay you don't worry about it
you don't get too serious about it I I
uh had a doctor recently you were there
I think she the the one in fly stuff she
said if this happen if this happen
you're going to die like that you know
and it's going to be terrible and I'm
like okay you know and she's like she's
like says do you she said she asked me
she doesn't know what I do she doesn't
know my occupation she says do you
meditate and I said a little bit and
she's
like you don't seem scared you
know okay so should be relaxed and happy
if you don't learn how to die you should
be nervous if you learn how to die you
should be relaxed and have a good time
before you go you know and okay I'm
going to go I'm taking the bus and I
know where it's going and I I know how
to what to do and I'm I'm okay and then
just you should not be so serious in
this club okay all right
questions and I feel better if Tim
choose do you feel comfortable Tim to
choose the an to choose the
questions
okay by the way keep coming to Lam okay
we'll come to Kono as much as we
can but keep coming it's good for you
it's really important okay and we won't
charge you there's no charge for the
class okay you you make it here you're
okay if Tim charge you let me
know
welcome oh microphone's not working I
think
[Music]
Ivan yeah that's
okay
yeah good question actually could you
repeat the question please I'm going to
repeat the question yeah let's say I do
do the right practice let's say I die
with B CH and I do go to a Buddha
Paradise well what's the what happens
after that normally do you stay there
until you become a Buddha or do you have
to come back here and suffer some more
and then go back to Buddha paradise and
then learn some more and like that so
generally if you die this way you go to
a Buddha Paradise you study with a
Buddha or many Buddhist there and then
you're finished and you get to stay
there you get to stay there permanently
okay so it's a good place it's a good
career
move uh to go to that Buddha Paradise
okay and they will teach you uh until
you become a Buddha you don't have to
come back here you can come if you want
to to help people but but you don't have
to like that
okay and
uh it's beautiful
to by the way you can see where you're
going if you meditate a lot you can see
what's next if you see emptiness you can
see 500 years ahead
okay you can see where you're going and
then it's much
more comfortable maybe one person out of
100 million knows where they're going
and they don't feel nervous and they
don't feel scared and they're fine
everything's fine you know where you're
going when you can see emptiness
directly and then you die I mean when
you see emptiness
directly you see where you're you're
going next and you even see who's going
to take care of you when you're a kid
you can see the teachers you know who's
the teachers so it's very relaxed you
know you you're like oh I know where I'm
going I know who's going to teach me and
they're really nice people super nice
people and you meet them when you're
just a baby and they'll take care of you
and you won't remember for about 15
years who who you
are uh and they they will take care of
you you make the karma that very very
good people will take care of you until
you remember who you are and it's very
beautiful and you see it directly so you
know you're on the airplane and the
plane starts going like this and
everyone's like ah and you're like yeah
okay let you know what's
coming but
and it's a wonderful
feeling you know to know where you're
going and to to be
sure and just relax then you can really
enjoy life I think most people cannot
enjoy life because they're deep down
they're scared I don't care if they
are you know great Soldier or something
everyone's scared to die I don't care
who you are people who commit suicide
are super scared to die
uh they're so scared they kill them
themselves you know so um if you can
touch emptiness directly then you know
where you're going you know how you're
going to die and you can relax and the
pressure is off and then you can really
have fun in this life I think only a
person who knows how to die can have
fun uh they they they can really have
fun
okay
thank you thank you Michael for teaching
so fun to be at you ready thank you she
looks so beautiful oh my God thank
[Applause]
you I want to ask you about
the sometimes I'm help uh Cancer
Foundation and there are families who
has kids with
cancer and the the parents and the kids
are asking why I have this illness and
why I have to be in a hospital and they
are making a lot of questions but H it's
so hard to say where is this coming from
because they are in a very deep
pain and what is the best way because we
cannot say what is the cost but what is
the best way to help them to have
answers and practice to to get better
seats yeah good question
okay there's
a yesterday in the car from the air
plane
airport uh I was uh translating
something and uh I got an email from
Aisha scus anaton Lan's white and she's
helping us find Sanskrit books and uh I
asked
her uh you know there's these caves in
China in the edge of the GOI desert and
they're called dunong caves and they
found many books there in a secret
wall behind the secret wall and they
found over 3,000 books right stany
something more and uh I was curious uh
what those books
are how good are the books there you
know I was curious did did the guy who
put the books there 1,400 years
ago did he know what he's doing or not I
was curious and uh and I asked Aisha to
make a list and it's very hard to find a
list because all the books were stolen
by different governments the the British
government stole a lot the French
government stole a lot the Russian
government stole a lot the American
government St a lot and it's very hard
to even find out the names of the books
and she worked hard and and she found
almost all of them and she made a list
and I was checking the list and I was
like whoa this guy knows what he's doing
you know I don't know who's this guy in
the cave but he's he really knows what
he's doing and there are eight
levels of teaching there I call it the
eight languages there's eight different
Buddhist languages it's so nice to be
able to say the word Buddhist in a
talk I'm always like boom
H so there's eight different levels of
Buddhism and uh six or seven of them
are are what do you call it they're not
the real
answer okay they're they're lower
schools of Buddhism all the eight
schools of Buddhism or the eight
languages of Buddhism and we're covering
all of them in our translation
team uh and they're all in dunong all of
them are in dunong which to me means
that guy knew what he's doing you know
uh but there's lower presentation and
there's higher presentation which
means uh when you teach a group of
people Any teacher who teach a group of
people first you have to watch their
faces you know if they go like
this then you have to change your Lang
language you have to move down the
language to a lower language you know
and then if they go
like or they fall asleep you have to
change the language again every time
Buddha
taught Buddha used one of eight
different languages depending on the
students okay some students are super
smart they're
like you know like sug gang when I first
met him I
mean he came to a talk with 1500 people
at the trade Union Auditorium in
Singapore I picked him out to Jenny Wong
do you remember I said go get that guy
he's he understands he's
like and uh if you see so you move up
and down the language letter it's the
same in the cancer word for the children
okay how much can you tell the children
how much can you tell the parents you
have to be a Buddha and you you have to
adjust your language you have to try try
this language if they look confused or
it's hurting them or something then you
go down and you go down down down down
until they look happy and then you
communicate on that level uh and you
communicate on that level for a while
and then you move up to the next level
and move up to the next level so it's
constant for all teachers all Buddhist
teachers even you're just a volun uner
in a cancer Children's Cancer Hospital
you have to speak the language of your
of your audience and we have an example
called
Buddha he's the example Buddha gave us
example I told my friend
uh I'll tell you a funny story I used to
take the bus to uh work because I don't
want to spend the money to buy a car for
for 19 years I I do four hours every day
on the bus for 19 years I I take the bus
because I I want to give the money to
the
Monas and I didn't buy a car and uh so
I one night the bus broke
down uh two hours you know and bu the
guy said everybody get off you know and
we're like What He says the next bus is
is coming in half an hour or what hour
they will stop and we're like it's cold
it's winter in New Jersey I'm so glad I
don't live in New Jersey anymore uh and
uh it's cold and it's terrible and
there's just a bar in there there's a
bar you know I'm like oh man let's see I
want to stay cold or I want to go in the
bar you know and it was a naughty bar
there was some bad shows going on and
and I was like God it's really cold you
know
so I went in the
bar and then I started teaching Dharma
to these two guys at the in the bar it
was so fun they're like really and I've
got this pen and the woman's going like
this and I'm like yeah this is pen you
know and they're whoa and then I thought
uh I had to drop down immediately to ABI
Dharma language you know like d d you
know so so uh use the language that they
can understand and I think uh it's very
important my teacher taught me you have
to respect their parents' wishes you
cannot teach them things that the
parents don't want you to teach so you
have to kind of check in with the
parents and see what's the level of the
parents and then there's always
something you can help there's always
good things you can say uh but I
think I think it's respectful to ask the
parents
or to you know see what the parents
reaction is and adjust your language
according to the parents reaction you
know but my experience is kids can
understand
everything kids can understand
everything so be bold also be bold with
them don't teach them something the
parents don't want you to teach but
don't be scared to say deep things
because kids are kids are really smart I
think every year we add to our life we
more stupid so kids are really
smart Tim we what's
up half an hour break you guys okay and
relax go PE PE have something to drink
it's uh it's not a great time a day to
have a class it's difficult to focus in
the evening so have some have something
to drink okay see you in a half an
hour